{"tossups": [{"question": "Experiments with the Moog synthesizer led Wendy Carlos to produce a \u201cSwitched-On\u201d version of this composer\u2019s work. This composer included a three-voice and six-voice ricercar [ri-TZER-car] in a collection of keyboard pieces based on a theme given to him by Frederick the Great. Despite being a devout Lutheran, he wrote a Catholic<em> Mass in B Minor</em>, and Felix Mendelssohn revived this man\u2019s work with an 1829 performance of his German-language<em> St. Matthew Passion</em>. For the point, name this Baroque composer of the Brandenburg Concertos.", "answer": "<b> J</b>ohann<b> S</b>ebastian<b> Bach</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "Caesar Rodney resigned this position in 1811 when he wasn\u2019t appointed to the Supreme Court. Elliot Richardson resigned this post rather than fire Archibald Cox. The current holder of this position required 166 days to be confirmed by the Senate. Edmund Randolph was the first to serve as, for the point, what head of the Department of Justice, a position currently held by Loretta Lynch?", "answer": "<b> Attorney General</b> of the United States", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "One member of this family refused to annul Henry VIII\u2019s marriage to Catherine of Aragon. Another member of this family was the mother of Louis XIII and wife of King Henry IV, and the Pazzi Conspiracy sought to assassinate members of this family. Girolamo Savonarola took control of a city after members of this family were expelled. Popes from this family include Clement VII and Leo X, and this family included Cosimo and Lorenzo the Magnificent. For the point, name this family of Grand Dukes from Florence.", "answer": "<b> Medici</b> Family", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "726 Kelvin. Its name was proposed in jest by a defender of the steady state theory, Fred Hoyle. Georges Lemaitre [le-MET] first proposed that this event occurred, comparing it to a \u201cCosmic Egg\u201d and the\u201cPrimeval Atom\u201d. For the point, name this cosmological event that occurred about 13.8 billion years ago.", "answer": "<b> Big Bang</b> theory Page 1", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Astronomy"}, {"question": "On this island, the Mamertines asked Rome for assistance against Hiero, whose ancestor Gelon had earlier defeated Carthage on this island at the Battle of Himera. This island was the target of a campaign led by Nicias [NIK-ee-us] and advocated for by Alcibiades [al-KIH-bee-AH-des]. Athens sent a failed expedition against Syracuse on, for the point, what island separated from Italy by the Strait of Messina?", "answer": "<b> Sicily</b> or<b> Sicilia</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "When one holder of this position was shot, he advised his secretary, George Cortelyou, to inform his wife carefully. Rose Mary Woods, another assistant to this position, stretched to reach a footpedal and a desk control to erase audio tapes; that caused an 18.5 minute gap in a recording of one holder of this post speaking with H.R. Haldeman, his Chief of Staff, about the Watergate break-in. For the point, name this post, which is also advised by the Joint Chiefs of Staff and a Cabinet including Secretaries of Defense and State, currently held by Barack Obama.", "answer": "<b> President</b> of the<b> U</b>nited<b> S</b>tates of America (prompt on partial answer)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Peng Dehuai criticized this movement at the Lushan Conference. This movement targeted rats, flies, mosquitoes, and sparrows in the Four Pests Campaign and sought to implement backyard steel furnaces. This plan caused at least 15 million deaths in the Great Chinese Famine. For the point, name this 1958-1961 plan by Mao Zedong to quickly industrialize China.", "answer": "<b> Great Leap Forward</b> (accept \u201cFour Pests Campaign\u201d before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "These people fought in the Battle of Island Mound, and one unit of these people suffered nearly 50% casualties while assaulting Fort Wagner. These people make up the majority of those killed in the Fort Pillow Massacre by Nathan Bedford Forrest. Robert Gould Shaw led this type of soldier, which formed the 54th Massachusetts Infantry Regiment. For the point, name these people, including two of Frederick Douglass\u2019 sons, who fought primarily for the Union during the Civil War, most of whom were former slaves.", "answer": "<b> African-American</b> soldiers (or<b> black</b> soldiers; accept<b> freed slaves</b> or equivalents before mentioned at end, but do not accept or prompt on slaves alone; do not accept Buffalo Soldiers)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In this city\u2019s reckless preparations for Expo \u201858, skyscrapers controversially replaced historic buildings like Victor Horta\u2019s Maison du Peuple. In 1989, Rue Justus Lipsius was removed for a building where the Council of Ministers usually meets. The European Parliament meets in Luxembourg, Strasbourg, and this city. For the point, name this headquarters of NATO, de facto capital of the EU, and capital of Belgium.", "answer": "<b> Brussels</b> (or<b> Bruxelles</b> or<b> Brussel</b>) Page 2", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "One player of this sport asked a world leader to \u201cdo him a solid\u201d and release prisoner Kenneth Bae, then visited that leader without discussing Bae\u2019s release. Another player of this sport raised millions of dollars for the Boys and Girls Clubs of America with an otherwise-controversial 2010 press conference in which he announced he was \u201ctaking his talents to South Beach\u201d. For the point, name this sport played by Dennis Rodman and LeBron James.", "answer": "<b> basketball</b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "Earthquakes under this body of water in 2007 revealed a 4,000-year-old fault line, on which a much stronger earthquake may have created a temporary land bridge. Despite losing its coastline on this body of water after a 1993 war of independence, Ethiopia still has use of its ports of Asseb and Massawa on this sea. For the point, name this body of water at the southern end of the Suez Canal that empties into the Indian Ocean through the Gulf of Aden and was legendarily parted by Moses.", "answer": "<b> Red</b> Sea (or<b> Erythrean</b> Sea or<b> Sea of Reeds</b>)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "A letter addressed to this person hoped that General Washington would fight against the \u201cdespotism of the petticoat.\u201d This person requested straight pins in one letter, and in another, she asked her husband to \u201cremember the ladies;\u201d those are among the roughly 1,200 known letters between this woman and her husband. For the point, name this second First Lady of the United States, the wife of John.", "answer": "Abigail<b> Adams</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In this country\u2019s south, Dravidian languages like Telugu and Tamil are spoken. This country\u2019s fifth most spoken language was primarily written using the Modi script until the 1950\u2019s. Its 1947 constitution creates no official language; government business here is bilingual, including English due to this country\u2019s colonial past. For the point, name this country on an Asian subcontinent where Hindi is spoken by hundreds of millions of people.", "answer": "Republic of<b> India</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "For the point, identify this term for the ability to process information and express knowledge, which can also describe information gathered by spy agencies like the American CIA.", "answer": "<b> intelligence</b> (accept<b> intelligence quotient</b> or<b> IQ</b>) Page 3", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Psychology"}, {"question": "In this city, police mistakenly shot Jean Charles de Menezes [me-NEZ-is] thinking he was a terrorist. In 2006, planes flying out of this city were targeted by a planned liquid-explosive terrorist attack. Two weeks after one terrorist attack in this city, an event of similar scale failed; both attacks involved targeting a bus and three subway trains along this city\u2019s \u201cTube\u201d. For the point, name this city which was attacked in 2005, a day after securing the 2012 Summer Olympics.", "answer": "<b> London</b>, England", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "One ruler of this empire, Manuel I, established a protectorate over the Crusader state of Outremer [oo-tre-MEHR]. The deposition of Andronikos I ended this empire\u2019s Komnenian Restoration. Earlier, its Alexius I asked for help at the Council of Piacenza against the Seljuks, which led Pope Urban II to call for the First Crusade. For the point, name this European empire that preceded the Ottoman Empire in modern-day Turkey.", "answer": "<b> Byzantine</b> Empire", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "During this battle, Edward Johnson sent a small reconnoiter that encountered James Wadsworth\u2019s 7th Indiana infantry on Culp\u2019s Hill. The high water mark of the Confederacy was reached at this battle, whose end was hastened by George Pickett\u2019s ill-fated charge up Cemetery Ridge. For the point, name this decisive three day battle in July 1863 which saw the largest number of casualties of any Civil War battle.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Gettysburg</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A 1979 trip by this world leader included a visit to Auschwitz and a mass in Krakow often credited with inspiring the Solidarity movement. For the point, name this man, born Karol Wojtyla [VOY-t\u2019wah] in Poland, who was Pope from 1978 to 2005.", "answer": "Pope<b> John Paul II</b> (prompt on \u201cJohn Paul,\u201d but do not prompt on \u201cJohn\u201d or \u201cPaul\u201d alone; accept Karol<b> Wojtyla</b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "Thomas Young, of double-slit experiment fame, worked on this object; his work proved helpful for Jean-Francois Champollion [shahm-POLE-ee-OHN]. This stele was surrendered to the British after it was discovered by soldiers in Napoleon\u2019s army near the port city of Rashid. A decree from Ptolemy V Epiphanes is inscribed on this object in the cursive demotic script and the Greek alphabet. For the point, name this Egyptian document inscribed with three languages that allowed the translation of hieroglyphics.", "answer": "<b> Rosetta Stone</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "Pavises were shields carried by soldiers who used this weapon. Richard the Lionhearted was killed by one of these weapons, and mercenaries wielding this weapon were most famously recruited from Genoa. The Chu Ko Nu is a repeating type of these weapons, which generally are slower to reload than their main alternative, the longbow. For the point, name these projectile weapons, which fire bolts instead of arrows.", "answer": "<b> crossbow</b>s (prompt on bow; do not accept or prompt \u201cbow and arrow\u201d or \u201clongbow\u201d)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "For extraditing the killers of Marcus Calpurnius Bibulus\u2019 sons, the Gabinians opposed this figure, who deposed Achillas and a brother influenced by Pothinus. Caesarion succeeded this half-sibling of Arsinoe IV [arr-SIN-oh-ee] after Marcus Agrippa won a naval battle, which prompted her to commit suicide via asp. For the point, name this pharaoh who lost the Battle of Actium, a co-ruler with Ptolemy XIII who loved both Mark Antony and Julius Caesar.", "answer": "<b> Cleopatra</b> VII Philopator", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "To relieve the Siege of Genoa, this man crossed the Lesser Saint Bernard Pass on a mule. This man forced the Treaty of Luneville after the Battle of Marengo, and he rose to prominence after the Siege of Toulon. This man technically won a victory at the Battle of Borodino, seven years after he destroyed the Third Coalition at Austerlitz. For the point, name this French Emperor, who was finally defeated at Waterloo.", "answer": "<b> Napoleon</b> Bonaparte I Page 5", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "In this war, Robert Ross\u2019s troops marched to the capital after winning the Battle of Bladensburg. The Chesapeake-Leopard Affair led Thomas Jefferson to issue an embargo on American exports, helping provoke this war. Andrew Jackson won the Battle of New Orleans after the signing of the Treaty of Ghent, which ended this war. For the point, name this war between Great Britain and United States that ended in 1815.", "answer": "War of<b> 1812</b> Page 6", "metadata": "History - American History"}], "bonuses": []}